(Music)
(موسيقى)
For any of you who have visited or lived in New York City,
بالنسبة لمن زار منكم أو عاش بـ نيويورك،
these shots might start to look familiar.
ربما بدت تلك اللقطات مألوفة.
This is Central Park,
هذه الحديقة المركزية،
one of the most beautifully designed
أحد أكثر الأماكن العامة
public spaces in America.
التي صممت بجمال.
But to anyone who hasn't visited,
ولكن، بالنسبة لمن لم يزرها،
these images can't really fully convey.
فلن يستوعب تلك الصور بشكل كامل.
To really understand Central Park,
لكي تفهم الحديقة المركزية بشكل حقيقي،
you have to physically be there.
يجب أن تكون هناك بجسدك.
Well, the same is true of the music,
حسناً، الأمر كذلك بالنسبة للموسيقى،
which my brother and I composed and mapped
والتي قمت أنا وأخي بكتابتها وفقا لخريطة
specifically for Central Park.
الحديقة المركزية على وجه الخصوص.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
I'd like to talk to you today a little bit about the work
أحب أن أحدثكم اليوم قليلاً عن العمل
that my brother Hays and I are doing --
الذي أقوم به مع أخي هايز --
That's us there. That's both of us actually —
ها نحن هناك. كلينا في الواقع --
specifically about a concept that we've been developing over the last few years,
حديثي تحديداً عن فكرة كنا نطورها خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية،
this idea of location-aware music.
تلك الفكرة عن الموسيقى الواعية بالمكان.
Now, my brother and I, we're musicians
الآن، أخي و أنا، نحن موسيقيان
and music producers.
ومنتجان للموسيقى.
We've been working together since,
نعمل معا منذ،
well, since we were kids, really.
حسناً، منذ أن كنا صغاراً، بالفعل.
But recently, we've become more and more interested
ولكن مؤخراَ، أضحينا أكثر انجذاباً
in projects where art
لمشروعات يكون الفن فيها
and technology intersect,
متقاطعاً مع التقنية،
from creating sight-specific audio
من تكوين صوتيات خاصة بالمواقع
and video installation
وتكوينات الفيديو
to engineering interactive concerts.
لهندسة الحفلات التفاعلية.
But today I want to focus on this concept
ولكن اليوم، أريد أن أركز على هذه الفكرة
of composition for physical space.
الخاصة بكتابة الموسيقى للأماكن المادية.
But before I go too much further into that,
ولكن قبل أن أمضي قدماً في ذلك،
let me tell you a little bit about how we got started
دعوني أخبركم عن الكيفية التي بدأنا بها
with this idea.
تلك الفكرة.
My brother and I were living in New York City
كنت أنا وأخي نعيش بمدينة نيويورك
when the artists Christo and Jeanne-Claude
عندما قام الفنانان كريستو وجين-كلود
did their temporary installation, The Gates,
بتكوينهم الفني المعاصر، البوابات،
in Central Park.
في الحديقة المركزية.
Hundreds of these brightly-colored sculptures
مئات من التماثل ذات الألوان البراقة
decorated the park for a number of weeks,
زخرفت الحديقة لعدد من الأسابيع،
and unlike work that's exhibited
وعلى عكس العمل الذي يعرض
in a more neutral space,
في أماكن متعادلة،
like on the walls of a gallery or a museum,
مثل جدران صالات العرض أو المتحف،
this was work that was really in dialogue
كان ذلك العمل في حالة حوار حقيقي
with this place,
مع المكان.
and in a lot of ways, The Gates
وبأكثر من طريقة، البوابات
was really a celebration
كان حقا احتفالاً
of Frederick Olmsted's incredible design.
بالتصميم الهائل لـ فريدريك أولمستيد.
This was an experience that stayed with us
ظلت تلك الخبرة معنا
for a long time, and years later,
لفترة طويلة، ولسنوات لاحقة.
my brother and I moved back to Washington, D.C.,
انتقلت مع أخي للعيش بواشنتن العاصمة،
and we started to ask the question,
وبدأنا نسأل،
would it be possible,
هل من الممكن،
in the same way that The Gates
وبنفس الطريقة التي استجاب عرض البوابات
responded to the physical layout of the park,
للتصميم المادي للحديقة،
to compose music for a landscape?
أن تُكتب موسيقي لموقع؟
Which brought us to this.
وهو ما جاء بنا لهذا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
On Memorial Day, we released "The National Mall,"
في اليوم التذكاري، أصدرنا "السوق القومي،"
a location-aware album
ألبوم موسيقي لموسيقى الوعي بالمكان
released exclusively as a mobile app
صدر حصرياً كتطبيق للهاتف
that uses the device's built-in GPS functionality
والذي يستخدم وظيفة تحديد المكان بجهاز الهاتف
to sonically map the entire park
ليرسم خريطة صوتية للحديقة بأكملها
in our hometown of Washington, D.C.
في مدينتنا واشنطن العاصمة.
Hundreds of musical segments
مئات من المقطوعات الموسيقية
are geo-tagged throughout the entire park
موسومة جغرافياً حول الحديقة بأكملها.
so that as a listener traverses the landscape,
بحيث أن المستمع وهو يجتاز الموقع،
a musical score is actually unfolding around them.
تنبسط أجزاء موسيقية حوله.
So this is not a playlist or a list of songs
فهذه ليست قائمة بأغنيات
intended for the park,
معنية بها الحديقة،
but rather an array of distinct melodies and rhythms
ولكنها، مجموعة من الألحان والإيقاعات المتمايزة
that fit together like pieces of a puzzle
والتي تتآلف مع بعضها كأجزاء الأحجية
and blend seamlessly
وتمتزج ببعضها دون ارتباط
based on a listener's chosen trajectory.
اعتماداً على ما يختار أن يذهب إليه المستمع.
So think of this as
ففكروا بهذا كـ
a choose-your-own-adventure of an album.
ألبوم ما تختاره لنفسك من مغامرة.
Let's take a closer look.
دعونا نلقي نظرة أعمق.
Let's look at one example here.
دعونا نأخذ هذا المثال.
So using the app,
حسناً، لنستخدم التطبيق،
as you make your way towards the grounds
وأنت تسلك طريقك في الأراضي
surrounding the Washington Monument,
المحيطة بنصب واشنتن التذكاري،
you hear the sounds of instruments warming up,
إنك تسمع أصوات الآلات الموسيقية تبدأ بالإحماء،
which then gives way to the sound of a mellotron
الذي يفسح المجال بعد ذلك لصوت الميلوترون
spelling out a very simple melody.
مشكلاً لحناً بسيطاً جداً.
This is then joined by the sound of sweeping violins.
ثم ينضم إلى هذا صوت الكمانات الجارف.
Keep walking, and a full choir joins in,
استمر في السير، و تنضم جوقة كاملة،
until you finally reach the top of the hill
حتى تصل في النهاية إلى قمة الهضبة
and you're hearing the sound of drums and fireworks
و أنت تسمع صوت الطبول و الألعاب النارية
and all sorts of musical craziness,
كل ألوان الجنون الموسيقي،
as if all of these sounds are radiating out
و كأن كل هذه الأصوات تشع
from this giant obelisk that punctuates
من النصب العامودي هذا الذي يحدد
the center of the park.
مركز الحديقة.
But were you to walk in the opposite direction,
لكن إن مشيت بالاتجاه المعاكس،
this entire sequence happens in reverse.
هذا الترتيب كله ينقلب.
And were you to actually exit the perimeter of the park,
و إن خرجت بالفعل من محيط المنتزه،
the music would fade to silence,
تتلاشى الموسيقى حتى تسكن،
and the play button would disappear.
و يختفي زر "شغِّل".
We're sometimes contacted by people in other parts of the world
أحياناً يتصل بنا أشخاص في أماكن أخرى في العالم
who can't travel to the United States,
الذين لا يستطيعون السفر إلى الولايات المتحدة،
but would like to hear this record.
لكنهم يودون سماع هذا التسجيل.
Well, unlike a normal album,
حسناً، على خلاف الألبوم العادي،
we haven't been able to accommodate this request.
نحن لم يكن بوسعنا الاستجابة لهذا الطلب.
When they ask for a C.D. or an MP3 version,
عندما يطلبون نسخة على الـ 'سي دي' أو كتسجيل رقمي 'إم بي 3'،
we just can't make that happen,
نحن لا يمكننا ببساطة تنفيذ ذلك،
and the reason is because
و السبب هو أن
this isn't a promotional app
هذا ليس تطبيق ترويجي
or a game to promote or accompany
أو لعبة للترويج أو لترافق
the release of a traditional record.
إصدار تسجيل صوتي تقليدي.
In this case, the app is the work itself,
في هذه الحالة، إن التطبيق هو المشروع بذاته،
and the architecture of the landscape
و الفن المعماري للمكان
is intrinsic to the listening experience.
هو من صميم تجربة الاستماع.
Six months later, we did a location-aware album
بعد ستة أشهر، قمنا بألبوم لموسيقى الوعي بالمكان
for Central Park,
لمنتزه سينترال بارك،
a park that is over two times the size of the National Mall,
هو منتزه أكبر بمرتين من حجم منتزه السوق القومي،
with music spanning from the Sheep's Meadow
يشتمل على موسيقى تترواح من موسيقى مرج الغنم
to the Ramble to the Reservoir.
إلى ترعد إلى الذخيرة.
Currently, my brother and I are working on
حالياً، أنا و أخي نعمل على
projects all over the country,
مشاريع في جميع أنحاء البلد،
but last spring we started a project,
لكن في الربيع الفائت بدأنا بمشروع،
here actually at Stanford's
هنا في الواقع، في قسم
Experimental Media Art Department,
ستانفورد لفن الوسائط التجريبي،
where we're creating our largest location-aware album to date,
حيث نقوم بابتكار أكبر ألبوم لموسيقى الوعي بالمكان حتى اليوم،
one that will span the entirety of Highway 1
هذا الألبوم الذي سوف يشمل كل "الطريق السريع رقم 1"
here on the Pacific Coast.
هنا على الساحل الهادي.
But what we're doing, integrating GPS with music,
لكن ما سوف نقوم به، أي دمج خاصية تحديد المكان بالموسيقى،
is really just one idea.
هي حقاً فكرة واحدة و حسب.
But it speaks to a larger vision
لكن الأمر يتطلع إلى رؤية أكبر
for a music industry that's sometimes struggled
من أجل صناعة الموسيقى التي قد جاهدت أحياناً
to find its footing in this digital age,
لتجد موطئ قدم لها في هذا العصر الرقمي،
that they begin to see these new technologies
بحيث قد بدؤوا بالنظر إلى هذه التقنيات الحديثة
not simply as ways of adding bells and whistles
ليس ببساطة على أنها طرق لإضافة تحسينات
to an existing model,
لنموذج حالي،
but to dream up entirely new ways
بل كطموح لابتكار طرق جديدة كلياً
for people to interact with
ليتفاعل الناس مع
and experience music.
تجربة موسيقية.
Thank you.
أشكركم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)